I don't think Dung had a policy that some should get rich first.
I think he was aware that in a country so large with more than one billion people,
it was impossible for everybody to get rich at the same time.
He knew that expectations would be very high.
That some people would think they can get ready right away.
And that they would be disappointed.
If they did not get rich quickly.
So his comment that some should get rich first was not a policy.
It was a way of talking to the people and getting them to realize that they should not expect
that everyone should suddenly get wealthy.
I believe that when he started his policies,
he understood that many cadres were afraid that after the culture revolution,
that anything they did could be criticized.
In the latter part of the culture revolution,
so many cadres had been criticized.
That many of them were very cautious.
Some of them concluded that the best way to get along is to do as little as possible
and not to take initiatives.
鄧小平 wanted the local cadres to take initiatives to do things.
He said in Chinese,
希望他们敢做,我希望那个人敢做,
so he wanted people to take courage.
And if he had criticized every little thing,
they would have been unafraid.
They would have been afraid to take big steps.
So he went lightly on cadres who would find ways to get rich a little bit themselves
or to help their friends.
If he knew that if he criticized too much,
then people would not be willing to take the courage to try new things and move quickly.
And he wanted things to move quickly.
And so they did.
The way I see it is that in a period of rapid growth,
there are so many changes and there are so many grey areas
that it takes a long time for any country to go through that transition.
If you look at the 19th century America,
when we first had big railways and we first had gold diggers and oil.
And some people got very,very rich very quickly and formed monopolies.
It took us many decades to develop rules and laws to adapt to the new situation.
China after 1978 grew and changed so rapidly
that there was no way they could have clear rules in 10 years or 20 years.
It is a long period of transition from the period of rapid growth
to the consolidation into a country with rules and regularity.
And China is still going through that transition
because it has changed so quickly
and is still not settling down yet.
I think Hu Jintao already made a serious effort
to deal with the problems.
His program to develop things for the west
was to reduce and eliminate rural taxation
and to help local schools in rural areas
was already a very important step in recognition
that they should now try to concentrate on the rest of the country.
Even in the late 80s,Deng Xiaoping wanted to have some policies
so that the wealth and progresson the east coast
and in the big cities would gradually spread to the other places.
I think what is now needed is further not only an attack on profiteering
and on extreme wealth
but a better taxation system
to reduce the extreme wealth
and more regular rules about what people can do.
Japanese companies were very successful
in limitinghow much the president of the company would make.
And in most Japanese companies,the highest salaries
and the lowest salariesare maybe six times
so that the person who is present in the company
is not so rich as in China.
But in China,the salaries were allowed to get much more extreme
and the riches from buying real estate
speculation have just gone way too high
and there should be more effortto tax those very rich people
and to limit the amount of salarydifferentials
between the highest and lowest salary.
Deng Xiaoping was never against democracy.
The term "mengyu"democracy always had good meanings
and at the time of democracy wallin December 1978
Deng Xiaoping told the visiting Japanese
why shouldn't people be allowed to express their opinions?
They have opinions,why shouldn't they express them?
and so for several weeks
he allowed people to continue to post things on the wall
but Deng Xiaoping felt the responsibility
for keeping order in the country.
Ever since the opium war,China had such disorder and confusion
that it was not possible to have growth.
He felt that in order for China to grow
you had to have stability.
And so after the democracy wall had gone in a few weeks
he felt it necessary to stop that
and to have it move to another place
some distance away
and the big wall in Sidan was closed down.
However,in August 1980
he gave a speech on political reform
and in 1986he allowed Zhao Ziyang
to conductmany discussions on political reform.
He was not against political reform.
In fact,I believe his so called four principles
Sigijibunyanzi that he announced
at the end of March 1979
were in effort to say
as long as you appreciate Mao Zedong
as long as we have respect for the party
and for the communist leadership
and for the dictatorship,the proletariat
we can have many discussions.
So it was to put a bottom line,a decent
and some things you could not discuss
but as long as you had that bottom line
then you can have a lot of discussion.
So I think Deng Xiaoping
was never opposedto democracy in the end.
He wanted moreand particularly to beginning
with more democracy in the party.
I think he shared the viewthat some of the errors
from the Great Leap Forward
and the Cultural Revolution
were made because it was not enough
inner party democracy
because not enough people expressed
their opinionthat the policies were wrong
and he feltthat that was not a good system
he wanted to find waysof promoting more discussion
but also of preventing things from getting out of hand.
Deng Xiaopingin 1978
realized thatin preparation for
opening and reformto have fast development
it would be useful to haveJapanese help.
Japanese had so much technology
so that in 1978
he already made a new treaty with Japan
even though Japan and China
normalized relations in '72
they had many issueswhich they had not yet settled
and it made it difficultfor Japanese investment
and Japanese technologyto come into China.
So he decidedin 1978to sign a new treaty
a peace and friendship
and thatallowedthe Japanese
and Chineseto work more closely together.
And when he wentto Japanin October 1978
he wanted to lay the conditions
for bringing new technologyinto China.
He visited a steel factory
perhaps the most modern steel factory in the world
at a place called Kimitsu
and that was the modelfor Baoshan
the first modern steel plant
and the Japanese transferred new technology.
He also visited a man named Matsushita
Sung Xia in Chinese
and who at the time
was the leading television maker
around the world
and modern electronic technology
so new electronic technology
he also visited Japanese Nissan factory
Riruchan
and that was a modern factory
that already had robots
so he wanted that technology
to come intoChina
and he also realized
that for all that process to go smoothly
he had to improvethe feelings
between Chinese and Japanese
so he visited the emperor
and had a good talkwith the emperor
who acknowledgedthat Japan
had done bad thingsin World War II
and thereforethe Japanese
and he also tried to give very much technology help
to China
and in 1980
when there was a public opinion poll
in Japanabout attitudes towardChina
78%of the Japanese people
had positive feelings towardChina
so that was a very good successful base
and under those circumstances
Deng Xiaoping felt both inside China
Weihao gentlemen
don't argue about things
and get down to work and accomplish something
and he felt in China and Japan
it should be the same way
Weihao gentlemen
so about those small islands
the islands themselves were not so important
what was important
was the broad relationship between Japan and China
and the building of a good relationship
so that technology and investment
and finance from Japan
could come to China
and he made that possible
and I think that helped Chinese modernization
after 1991,92
because of the collapse of the Soviet Union
there was no longer a strategic environment
where the United States, Japan and China
were all allies against the Soviet Union
that had changed
so it was harder to be friends with Japan
but since that time
the tensions between Japan and China have grown
I personally believe
as one who goes to Japan all the time
I consider myself a friend of China
I consider myself a friend of Japan
I first went to Japan in 1958
I've been going every year for over 50 years
and stay there a long time
I think the Chinese press
is not report accurately the situation in Japan
the people actually
have very much rejected World War II
they have rejected militarism
and Japan still has many good qualities
it has high quality production
it has long life
the longevity of the Japanese people
is the highest in the world
it has very good educational program
it has very low inequality
it has some of the best energy policies
and saving of pollution
controller pollution in the world
and in my view
it is still in China's interest
to have better relations with Japan
and to have in the media
more information about the actual current situation
in the Japanese public
I do not look at all of Chinese television
but from what I understand
there are many movies of World War II
and not many that show the ordinary life
of the Japanese people
and the ordinary attitudes of the Japanese people
so I think in China
there is not a good understanding
of the current situation in Japan
of course there are some old people
who are still alive
who remember the horrible things
that Japan did in World War II
I think that there is not a mood
in China to have a good positive understanding
of Japan
and in the case of Japan
when Japanese reporters
report the experience
for example
when Chinese youth
through stones at the house
of the Japanese ambassador in Beijing
that those pictures are shown in Japanese TV
and when the Chinese youth
through stones at stores
in Japanese products in China
that is shown on Japanese TV
and when your ships
and your airplanes
go near Yajidao
that is shown on Japanese TV
so that has given the Japanese
a very bad impressionof China
so now
if you do a public opinion poll
less than 10% of the people
have positive feelings toward China
and in 1980 after Dunn's visit
it was 78%
so I think the situation in China
also has a big impact
on how Japanese feel toward China
I think if the Japanese press
was reporting more favorable attitudes
about the daily life of the Japanese
and the daily attitudes
I think that the situation could improve
I think in Japan
they also need to do a better job
in informing their people
about the horrors of World War II
in fact most Japanese realize
they did bad things in World War II
and they know the horrible things
but they don't know the details
and I think the Japanese
should do a better job
I say this in Japan also
they should do a better job
of informing their young people
about the horrors
that happened in World War II
including Nanjing
and in Northeast and so forth
he would go back to his policy
putting the 假日出 on the shelf
and try to have better relations
he would want more movies
about daily life in Japan
he would want to promote more exchanges
between young people
and between local communities
and he would
try to change
the reporting in Chinese media
so that there are more things
about daily life
and the accurate information
about Japanese life
so that they could improve the relations
after all
I think he is right
that China and Japan live next to each other
in the long run
they cannot become enemies
and it is not in the interest of China
to make Japan into an enemy
so I think that many Chinese people
do not realizethat their attitudes
are encouraging more military spending
in JapanChina is worried about that
but ifthey continue their
sending airplanes and ships
to the 假日出
and they continue in their own TV
so many movies about world war 2
and so few about current life
then I think the Japanese
will become more military
their military expenses will grow
I think more Japanese have shown
that they are ready to have high level discussions
and I think more high level meetings
by leaderscould improve
it is very important
and trust does not build easily quickly
but I think that this year
for the APEC meetings in November
is the time when Japanese leaders
will come to China
I think it is a good time
for some leaders on both sides to meet
one Japanese leader
Fukuda,Futien came to Japan
China recently and had some discussions
and Chinese son of Huiaobang
Hudaping recently went to Japan
I think those are very good beginnings
Li Xiaolin also went to Japan recently
so I think those are hopeful signs
I think those meetings should continue and grow
I think those are hopeful signs
It is hard to say
my hope is that the high leaders
of China and Japan, Xi Jinping
and now Obama can continue to have more talks
we are beginning to have military talks
these are very good signs
but American businessmen
and Beijing are now very worried
about the anti-monopoly
Fundenege Lundanjuida
they understand that if China has problems
with foreign monopoly
they can take steps
we would agree with that
we don't want our policy
and our country to have monopoly
but many American businessmen
feel that that movement
is now being used to discriminate
against foreign business
to make it tough for all foreign business
and so they are not so optimistic
about the future of foreign business in China
and I am worried about that
because when our Congress
makes decisions about China policy
the businessmen usually say
we want to have good relations with China
but if they become pessimistic
about their future in China
then our Congress would be less willing to cooperate
so I see both tendencies now
some tendencies at the top
they have better relations
and some worries at lower levels
because some Chinese military
feel confident that ever since the opium war
they were oppressed by the outside world
that the outside world pushed too much on them
and that they want to now find a chance
to get backfinding China is strong enough
we don't need to give in anymore
that attitude I can understand
but I think it could lead to dangerous confrontation
that will lead to other countries
if China tries to show they are strong and tough
then other countries will respond
by trying to show they are tough and strong
so in balance I see both tendencies
and I hope that the tendency
to cooperate at the very top
by Xi Jinping and Obama
and by the military beginning to have real talks
and by scholars and exchange programs
increasing understanding
I am cautiously optimistic
that that side will turn out to be more important
but I see both tendencies now
when some forward more cooperation
goodwill understanding
and some toward more tensions
I think that in the next year
I don't expect major changes
my hope is that this year in November
we can have a gradual understanding
between some high level leaders on both sides
I think within five years
the chances of the relationship will get better
so my hope is that in over five to ten years
the relationship will again begin to improve
and get back to the 1980s
so that is my hope
and I think both sides need to do work
I think the Japanese side needs to train
their younger people to understand
how bad Japan military was in China
why so many people Chinese are upset
and I think the Chinese need to have
a more accurate understanding
of the daily life in Chinain Japan
I think it is natural
that when you have opening of markets
and opportunities
that many people will begin to think of themselves
and their families
rather than the collective good
I think that is very hard to capture
I think in the United States we have similar problems
after World War II when we fought the Nazis
and we fought Japan
we had many Americans who thought of the overall good
and not just the personal good
and the good of their party or their family
and there is no easy answer
but I think in China
the example of the leadership
is very important
that if the Chinese public
feel that the leadership is not corrupt
and if they feel they are working hard
for the country
and that the local party leadership
is working hard for the country
then I think they are more public minded
and less selfishand less egotistical
and it is important for the Chinese leaders
to show to their people
that they set that proper example
I think at the early stage of economic reform
people were so poor
they had so little to eat
that they just wanted to concentrate
on finding enough food
and in getting a home
to their children educated
and getting medical care
for old people
and saving money for old age
but once they begin to do that
then they say what is the purpose of life
what are we doing
and many Chinese now are at that stage
they already have the basic necessities
for a comfortable life
and they say what is the purpose of life
why are we together
and they are looking for something bigger
and we have the same thing
in western countries too
some people who are so busy
with their personal things
they don't think about the bigger picture
and faith in big religions
in the united states
is not as strong as it was
sixty years ago
but some of it is coming back
in a very unsophisticated way
but I think people are searching
for some higher meaning
and I see that in China
as well as in other countries
the idea of crossing
the river by grouping for stones
is not unique to Deng
other people said it before
it's an old such one saying
and it was an idea before
and even in the 1950s
China is large enough
so they had certain experiments
even in something like carrying out land reform
you try it certain places
and then expand it to other areas
and I remember the expression
some dian
dao xian
some xian diao nian
you try it in a spot
then try bigger way
and then on a broader scale
so I think that in a country as large as China
that idea of experimentation
in a small placeis not unique to Deng
what I thinkhappened in his period
after 1978
was that he led that policy
in new directions of opening and reform
and I think that's still happening now
so even if China
passes the United States
an overall economic growth
an overall economic GMP
in a decade or so
China still has the problem
of adapting to the world
and the idea of experimenting still makes sense
China is large or small
because it has such a large population
such a large area
it's not like a tiny country
if a tiny country tries a policy
that's the policy of the whole country
but China is so big
they can still try things in certain areas
and expand to others
first of all I think the world understanding
the birth of the bubble problem in Japan
does not give the whole picture
I think most of the newspapers
stories about Japan
are for the people who want to invest
and so with Japan
the economy not growing much
they say Japan is a failure
things they have not tried
and everything
but if you consider from another perspective
ordinary life in Japan
is still very good
and now everybody has
over 90% have a good standard of living
have good health care
have long life
and have good education
and the inequality problems
are getting a little worse
but not so bad
I think in other words
that Japan is not as bad
if you look at the whole picture of the society
and once China gets to a high standard of living
and growth will decline
that even though growth may in say 10 years
maybe down to 3% or 5% a year
that's not a bad thing
but in the circumstances
then China needs to concentrate
on different areas
helping the poor areas
helping raise the standard
getting better health
and so economic growth
is not the only thing in the world
and I think that there are some specific lessons
but not letting the bubble get too big
the economic policy specialists can learn from Japan
I think that in the late 1980s
after the Plaza agreement
the Japanese let the bubble economy get too big
and they should have managed it
but I think in many other ways
Japan has managed social developments
and energy policy
and employment policy in a very good way
and I think in all those areas
China still has things to learn from Japan
it's very difficult to have a policy that works everywhere
when you have a private economy
because the private economy
is hard for government to control in a precise way
but I think if the government has enough money
to give fairly good salaries to its workers
and has moderate differences
but not huge differences
and then can control the private wealth
from getting too big
somemy Chinese taught me a new word in Chinese
this year, this week
too how
that many billionaires are not so sophisticated
and I think that if you can put some limits
on the amount of money that those people have
find policiesand then through taxation
of those really rich people
and then use some of that money
to increase the basic salaries
of salaried workers for the government
and for state enterprises
that would be a good thing
I think in the 1950s
a lot of very smart Japanese specialists
realized that many workers were opposed to new technology
they were afraid that if you brought in technology
they would lose their jobs
so the leaders of the businesses made a deal
they would be open and give information
they would give a large percentage of the profits
to the workersand not just to the capitalists
and those basic agreements
will work out in the 1950s
I think that a great deal
to make Japanese society fairly stable today
what I try to dowhen I look at an issue
is consider the issue from all aspects
from the immediate people around someone
for the local groups were there
for the broader society
for international relations
and for historical developments
I try to think about each of those
and I think if you consider
start from the very broad picture
what happened in Chinese history
and world history as a result of Daum
and the leadership that he provided
he made it possible
for China to enter into the world
it had always in history
been a leader of Asia for several thousand years
but it had never joined the international institutions
and since the 18th century
in Europe and North America
there were gradually new international laws
and rulesand it grew immediately
after World War II
Dung helped guide China
into that new world structure
he joined the world bank
he joined the international monetary portion
he laid the basisfor joining
the World Trade Organization
and China benefited enormously
from the international trade
so I think many young Chinese
do not realize how hard that was
some young Chinesethink the problems now are so difficult
but they don't realize how difficult
the things were in 1978
I know some of my Chinese friends
from the left criticizeDung
becausehe did not do enough
it was a very difficult
pay between rich and poor
and he allowedcorruption to grow too much
some of my people
and a lot of things to get too capitalistic
some of my friends
who are more rightin China
think they did not do enough for democracy
and ifhe had done more for democracy
and freedom,China would be better today
maybe they are partly right
but if you consider the broad development
if you consider China after the end
of the cultural revolution
when the society was so poor
so badly divided
the problems of bringingChina into the world order
which all the leaders Sunniatsen
Junka Shek had failed
and Mao Zedong had failed
and he had done the leadership
that happened
and he had extraordinary political leadership
so my conclusion is
that from the standard of the overall impact
of the society he faced
and what he accomplished
that there was an enormous change
that was under his direction
and I did not see that any other Chinese leader
had the experience,the wisdom
the experience abroad
the experience in all kinds of areas
in foreign relations
and the economy and local government
no one else had that combination
of experience and leadership
who could have guided China
at that critical period
I think Chinese people were very lucky
that such a strong leader
maybe he could have done more
to make China more equal
to make China free
those are very hard judgments
and history does not allow
hypotheses
it's either happened and so we see what happened
and I think it is remarkable
what happened under his leadership